it's a Bunty I'm facing a dilemma my
parents want me to pursue a family and a
successful business
believing it will bring happiness and
Merit for the both of us
however I see this as unbeneficial in
the context of samsara if I choose
monastic life I'll disobey my parents
and hurt them as they don't value the
dhamma is there a way to avoid causing
them pain while following my path
no no you can't have it both ways
on one hand you have you have a goal
that's kind of
easier to accomplish in a way more
palpable more satisfactory to more
people get your family
get your family
job look after parents
uh on the other hand but then you know
it has its Limited
benefits benefits are kind of
to this life and even that's
questionable for guaranteed it's not
guaranteed that you'll be sickness free
and aging and and death so that that's
unavoidable and it might come sooner
than expected so
plus lots of other factors can come in
the way on the other hand you have a
task that would obviously displease
everybody around you be much harder to
accomplish much more uncertain to
succeed at but if you do then you're
done you have ended the samsara for you
you have ended the samsara for you
so it's just like how what type of
vision you have whether it's
short-sighted alongside it are you
courageous enough or not
but you can't you can't go both ways you
can't it's impossible
and also if you think like oh well you
know I'll do one for a bit then I'll do
the other one later
theoretically I suppose that's possible
but practically the longer you stay
engaging with a household life hustle duties
with a household life hustle duties
Rejoice accumulating results of the
actions of a householder the more burden
is accumulated which means going to be
harder and harder to give it up because
it's it's it's it's the more time it
passes it's going to start to concern
more and more people not just you and
your parents
and then it will be factually harder to
to sever the Styles so it's not a it's
not a the status quo it's not it's not
going to stay a neutral thing that then
you can just switch 20 years from now on
no the burden will be there binding you
even harder
so
you want to be basically you want to
make that decision
sooner rather than later and then uh stick to
rather than later and then uh stick to
it and
we come up with this kind of uh meet
many people who come up with this
dilemma yeah I mean it was in the suit
as often as well you know parents
leaving the family you don't want to
duty yes but you think do they know
what is beneficial well that's the thing
like see back back in India
you leave your family
if you were the only son there was a
good chance they probably won't live
much longer
or when they reach the old age that's it
you're worth their insurance policy but
that's not the case today
so you might displease them but hardly
parents today would be existentially
threatened If the child leaves certainly
if you come from the Western Society
you know there is plenty of of systems
in order that that you wouldn't need and
mind you even people that whose children
don't leave them they
they're not you know the children don't
look after the parents it's just not
right there's so many other ways so it's like
there's so many other ways so it's like
then you want to also re let's just
check basically is it just you're gonna
cause the mental discomfort and upset
and disappointment
and don't conflate that with like oh no
they really need me for their survival
which is most likely not the case
but either way you're gonna have to take
responsibility if you choose to appease
to them you you can't then later on in
your life complain because you chose
what they wanted over what you wanted
and you have to stick to that now and
everything that comes out of it 20 years
later it's on you
you can't blame your parents or anybody
you made that choice
and same if you choose to pursue the way
out of samsara and go the uncertain path
build up the courage it's on you
any suffering that your parents have
upset disappointment it's on you
so you can't because you have to accept
it and then again if you practice
successfully you will find a way out of
it without needing to to abandon your
practice in the Dharma but that is
conditional upon successful practice
you could use it as a as an inspiration
and a a criteria and a threshold
for the successfulness of your practice
like are you able
to Bear the weight
of leaving your parents
incurring them suffering
uh to do what you want not doing what
they want
from you despite them raising you
investing the whole life in you
are you able to endure that
practice rightly not be moved by it
so each time you get careless in your
practice just remember what's at stake
the welfare your parents that you
abandoned so can you afford then to be careless
so can you afford then to be careless
and mess around and oh today I'll ignore
my intentions and I like that of
sensuality because this is what you caused
because this is what you caused
that's that's quite interesting because
you can use that remembering
if your parents are hurt by your going
forth you can use that as a motivation
to do the right thing which is actually
the right thing yeah which could lead in
the future then
do you look if if you had to succeed
even just
a little bit being virtuous and then
finding peace in that and and well that
is the most meritorious for them again
if you you had to your parents had to
then meet you again at that point
and they were good enough parents they
were at least recognize that their son
their daughter was actually happy
actually doing quite well and that would
then make them happy as well you would
even if it doesn't be worth it even if
he doesn't the fact that they would have
raised a being an individual that has
now become established in virtue and
Right View and efforts and so on they
will partake in that
because you wouldn't be where you were
if they haven't raised you rightly
so that's something it's beneficial for
them as well but yeah it's a they might
not see it
but yeah it's a good if you have
compassion for them of course if there
is an opening for them to hear it to
learn from you
which they might be and it's probably a
good likelihood you know if sometimes
they pass they'll come around and accept
that and so on
but uh either way it's not going to be
easy
if you choose to stay because it feels
like oh you're gonna appease more people
sooner and it feels safer is it though
I mean you might not see tomorrow things happen
things happen
and what
what have you uh basically you gave up
the whole opportunity
for a complete freedom and Escape
on a kind of something that
that you didn't even get to do
because again people do assume they're
going to live forever so when they make
these plans about the future and family
and job and looking after parents the
years decades ahead it's like
okay yeah but do you have that much time
how do you even know that
so if you were to think more acutely
uh more in a more disciplined manner of
your situation
that liability to sickness aging and
death is not 30 years from now on
it's always the same always equal from
the day you were born
then you you would I think it would be
easier to make this decision you would
not you would not you would not even be
considering really you will not be
weighing these options
because again one not just that it's
even more uncertain
but you might not even get to actually
develop it the way you were hoping
even if you had to have the perspective
of what you just said
death all the time is there for you
basically even if you have that perspective well
even if you have that perspective well
if you have that perspective and then
the world is telling you that you're
wrong no no no no oh that's relevant nothing
no no no no oh that's relevant nothing
can come in between that yeah well just
experience that anxiety of things could
end it doesn't matter who says what it
will make a difference to that
recognition and if it does it's when you yourself
and if it does it's when you yourself
forget it
because or I think you're you're kind of
absolved from it
uh that's when when you start
considering these um long-term things
that in forgetting how uncertain the
factory are and how contingent they are
upon all sorts of things that are not in
your control
your health other people's health
circumstances everything else around you
so
you're not sure about your your
perspective that you have that death is
always present you're not sure about
that really if the world starts to say
to you no
that's not the way it is forget it it's
about life yeah it hasn't sunk in it
hasn't sunk in then yeah
you're suede still
yeah the world
yeah I mean
even asking question a question or can I
have both how can I do both it's already
like you know the answer there so you just
you know the answer there so you just
you're just hoping reaching for strolls
basically you want to hear something
magical they would absorb you from
responsibility either way but I'm saying
the opposite
you're going to accept responsibility
for both
so if you stay with your parents you
have to accept responsibility for
everything that comes out of it and for
not pursuing the practice and liberating
yourself if you go and pursue the practice for
if you go and pursue the practice for
liberating yourself you have to accept
the full responsibility for that
whenever you're slacking non-diligent
lazy gonna accept that and the fact that
you close your parents immense amount of
pain so not just that you can't have both
so not just that you can't have both
you're going to have even less either
way
but that is still more right than lying
to yourself about it
if you become a monk then your
responsibility not just that it doesn't
diminish it doubles up
and that's a good thing